Finding Aid for Galens Medical Society records, 1914-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Galens Medical Society records 1914-2001
Galens Medical Society.
9859 Bimu 2
Student Honorary Medical Society at the University of Michigan Medical School, conducts annual "Tag Day" fund-raising campaign in support of its charitable activities and produces the Smoker, an annual musical parody produced and performed by medical students; papers include minutes and other organizational records, historical sketches of the organization, photographs documenting the founding and growth of the society and audio-visual recordings of Galens Smoker
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
8 linear feet
5.5 GB online
The record group (donor no. 8731 ) was received in June 1998. Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The Galens Honorary Medical Society was founded in 1914 as an honor society for upperclassmen in the university medical school. According to its original constitution, its purpose was to foster mental and social relationships between faculty and upperclassmen and between fraternity members and independents. The society's other goals included standing for the honor system and inviting leading medical professionals to speak to the club or in classes. In the following decades, the Galens broadened their activities and membership. In 1975, they revised their constitution, defined themselves as a service organization, and renamed themselves the Galens Medical Society. Their new statement of purpose reflected years of development in its emphasis on assisting underprivileged and crippled children, providing loans and scholarships for medical students, promoting medical education and scholarship, and furthering the activities and traditions of the university medical school.
From 1914 to 1948, membership in the society was divided into two categories: active and honorary. The society elected twenty to twenty-five active members from the junior and senior classes. About two-thirds of the students belonged to fraternities. Honorary members were elected from previous Galens who remained actively connected with the University of Michigan. The society also elected faculty prefects to serve as advisors for one to two years. In 1948, the Galens limited the number of active members from any one fraternity and distinguished between alumnus membership and honorary membership. They elected honorary members from the medical school male faculty, even if they had not been a Galen previously. In 1954, membership expanded to twenty-eight members and has grown ever since. In the 1960s, when election procedures for new active members were questioned, they considered other procedures for electing new members, such as faculty or self-nominations. They eliminated the minimum fraternity membership requirements in 1968 and admitted women in 1971. Sophomores were admitted by 1982, and freshmen were included by 1988. With the new election procedures, membership swelled to over one hundred fifty members in the 1980s and 1990s.
From the early years of the Galens, the society represented the opinions and needs of the student body. For example, in 1916 they helped to establish a uniform honor system for the university medical school. They submitted annual recommendations that represented student concerns about the required curriculum and the quality of instruction. In the 1930s and 1940s, they equipped student laboratories and lecture halls. In the 1940s and 1950s, they provided free tuberculosis examinations for medical students. They maintained various lounges in the school and hospital from the 1940s to 1970s. From 1940 to the present, they have sponsored an annual lectureship as well as loans and scholarships for medical students. From the 1950s to the present, the Galens have oriented freshmen to the medical school. They also have presented awards to students, residents, and faculty. Since 1937, they have annually awarded a faculty member with the "Silver Shovel" for the "gift of gab." Since 1976, they have presented the "Bronze Beeper" to staff at core medical school hospitals who have best contributed to medical students' education. In addition, the Galens have sponsored social activities. They have held an initiation banquet annually since 1915, and they have organized the Caduceus Ball since 1934.
The first Tag Days in 1927 marked the beginning of the Galens' public service tradition to benefit hospitalized children. During two days in December, Galens aggressively canvassed the streets of Ann Arbor for donations. Donors received a red or green tag to wear as a sign of their support. Galens also solicited donations by mail. The proceeds initially sponsored Christmas parties for children in the university hospital and provided equipment and a part-time instructor for the Galen Shop. In the Galen Shop, hospitalized children created arts and crafts. Proceeds from later Tag Days supported a small library, roof garden, and salaries for personnel to bring crafts to children's bedsides. In 1964, the Galens donated $30,000 for the construction of a new children's workshop in the new Mott Hospital, yet also decided to give Tag Day proceeds to other organizations that benefited children. In 1968, the society pledged $80,000 to equip the "Galens Intensive Care Unit for Children" in the Mott Hospital. In 1974, they pledged $100,000 over ten years for the new pediatric unit of St. Joseph Mercy Hospital. In 1982 when the unit was not finished as planned, the Galens were forced to reconsider the appropriation of Tag Day funds. They required all charitable groups, except the Children's Workshop at the Mott Hospital, to submit annual proposals for use of Tag Day funds. The organizations had to be in Washtenaw County, benefit children under eighteen years of age, and have exhausted other forms of funding. For example, in 1990-1991 the Galens distributed nearly $71,000 among thirteen organizations that assisted children (Box 2, Officers' Records and Reports, President, 1993-1994, Galens Honorary Information Packet).
From the 1970s to 1990s, the Galens have participated in a number of other service activities. For example, they performed free physicals in the Ann Arbor and Ypsilanti area for children attending camp. They staffed free health clinics for underprivileged children in Ypsilanti and at the Packard Community Clinic. They also staffed the Briarwood Run and organized Red Cross blood drives.
Outside of donations, dues, and Tag Days, from 1938 to 1972 the Galens acquired funds from the Galen News Stand in the hospital lobby. The store fund provided money for social activities, medical charities, equipment for the medical school and hospital, loans, awards, and miscellaneous expenses. The news stand was closed when profits plummeted due to the discontinuation of cigarette sales.
In 1918, the society held its first "All-Medic Smoker" in the Michigan Union. In the show, students and professors gave informal humorous dialogues to a male audience in a smoke-filled room. By the 1930s, the humor of the Smoker was patently irreverent and risqué. The 1931 Smoker saw the introduction of Thymico-Lymphatic Constitution, a satirical, partly obscene newspaper. When the 1948 edition crossed the desk of the Dean of Students, he responded with a suspension of their social privileges. After a year, medical faculty intervened to restore the Galens activities. Beginning in 1955, the society attempted to clean up the humor of the skits. From 1961 to the present, the Society has parodied movies and musicals in order to poke fun at life in medical school, with titles such as "My Fair Malady" and "The Sound of Mucus." Admission of women to the Smoker was a hotly contested issue until the Galens admitted women as members to the society in 1971.
Overall, this record group documents the changing concerns of medical students for their education, medicine, and community. It shows the Galens' evolution from an exclusive, junior and senior, male honorary society to an inclusive service society open to all medical students. It documents the growth of the society's funds and involvement with the university hospital and charities in Washtenaw County. It highlights the society's interactions with other students, faculty, alumni, community organizations, and Washtenaw area residents, and reveals the different perceptions each has had of the society's goals, membership, and activities. The humor and social activities of the society also reveal a lighter side to medical student life.
The Galens also maintain a website at http://www.umich.edu/~galens.
This Galens Medical Society record group documents the activities, goals, and membership of the organization from 1914 to 2011. It reveals the changing purpose and membership of the society, its traditional social functions, and its contributions to the medical school, university hospital, and Washtenaw County groups that benefit children. The record group is arranged in nine series: Minutes, Officers' Records and Reports, Activities and Funds, Histories and Constitutions, Membership, Audio-Visual Material, Funds, Service Activities, and Smoker.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Medical School--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.; Charities--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Children--Health and hygiene--Michigan.
- Minutes 1914-2001
  The Minutes, 1914-2001 (1.0 linear ft.), series contains three forms of information about the society's meetings. Minutes were kept in books and on individual sheets in annual files. Galens also provided typed summaries of minutes from 1914 to 1920. Annual histories in the Histories and Constitutions series fill in gaps in the minutes between 1932 and 1944. Recent minutes are available on the Galens website: www.umich.edu/~galens.
  - Books (Box 1)
    - 1914-1932 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1954-1958, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - Files
    - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Summaries 1914-1920 (Box 1)
- Officers' Records and Reports 1939-1996
  The Officers' Records and Reports, 1939-1996 (1.25 linear ft.), series includes the records of the president and treasurer. The presidents' records and reports contain the best sources of continuous information about the yearly activities of the Galens between 1945 and 1995. Most folders contain the annual president's report, which details the accomplishments and activities of the Galens society for the academic year. Reports can be found for most, but not all years, and include descriptions of the major activities of the group such as the initiation banquet, tag days, smoker, and lectureships. The reports also contain various correspondence to and from the president, financial summaries, and lists of award recipients and honorary members.
  The treasurers' records and reports document the finances of the Galens between 1939 and 1995. Most folders contain an annual report submitted by the treasurer summarizing the activity of each of the funds maintained by Galens. Various pieces of correspondence to and from the treasurer can also be found among the files. Additional financial and fund information can be found in the Activities and Funds, and the Funds series. The Galens were required to keep more accurate financial records after 1976 to maintain their status as a non-profit corporation and their permit to solicit funds during Tag Days.
  - President (Box 2)
    - 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - 1945-1946 (Box 2)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 2)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1965, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1967-1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 2)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer
    - 1939-1960 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 3)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 3)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 3)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
- Activities and Funds 1929-1999
  The Activities and Funds, 1929-1999 (1.25 linear ft.), series includes the reports and records of the various committees responsible for organizing activities or appropriating funds. Highlights of this series include records documenting the coordination of Tag Days, reports and photographs of the Galen Shop, where hospitalized children made crafts. Most committees only sporadically collected their records or wrote reports. Therefore, summaries in the Officers' Records and Reports series fill in the gaps of this series.
  - Awards 1950-1984 (Box 3)
  - Briarwood Run 1994 (Box 3)
  - Children's Fund 1954, 1962-1967 (Box 3)
  - Financial Allocations Committee 1974-1994 (Box 3)
  - Foreign Fellowship 1961-1971, undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Galen News Stand (Store)
    - Committee Reports and Transfers 1940-1966 (Box 3)
    - Financial Statements and Charts 1946-1972 (Box 3)
  - Galen Shop
    - 1929-1930 (Box 3)
    - 1930-1931 (Box 3)
    - 1931-1932, 1932-1933 (Box 3)
    - 1933-1934, 1934-1935 (Box 3)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 3)
      (includes photographs)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 3)
    - 1937-1938, 1938-1939 (Box 3)
    - 1939-1940, 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - 1941-1942, 1942-1943 (Box 3)
    - 1944-1945, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - 1946-1947, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
    - 1948-1949, undated (Box 3)
    - Articles and Pamphlets 1937 undated (Box 3)
  - Galens Intern and Resident Loan Fund 1959-1960, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - General Fund 1953-1960, undated (Box 3)
  - Initiation Banquet
    - Invitations and Programs 1947-1995 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Reports 1940-1990 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Job Survey Committee 1964-1966 (Box 3)
  - Laboratory Committee 1949-1966, undated (Box 3)
  - Lectureship (1940 undated) (Box 3)
  - Lounges 1957-1969 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Medical Student Loan Fund 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (undated) (Box 3)
  - Operations Committee 1965-1966 (Box 3)
  - Orientation Picnic 1985-1986 (Box 3)
  - Publicity 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Scholarship Fund 1940-1960 (Box 3)
  - Social Action 1974-1986 (Box 3)
  - Social Events 1956, 1964, 1965, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
  - Student-Faculty Associate Program 1954 (Box 3)
  - Student-Faculty Committee 1959-1966 (Box 3)
  - Tag Days (Box 4)
    - 1956, 1957, 1960, 1961 undated (Box 4)
    - 1962, 1963, 1964, 1966 (Box 4)
    - 1968, 1969, 1970 (Box 4)
    - 1971, 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973, 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975, 1976, 1977 (Box 4)
    - 1978, 1979 (Box 4)
    - 1980, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984 (Box 4)
    - 1985, 1986 (Box 4)
    - 1987, 1988 (Box 4)
    - 1989, 1990, 1991, 1992 (Box 4)
    - 1993, 1994, 1996, 1999 (Box 4)
  - Taxes
    - Exempt Status Information 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - 990 Forms 1982-1984, 1986-1988 (Box 4)
  - Triennial Medical Alumni Banquet 1953-1964 (Box 4)
  - Tuberculosis Program 1948-1956 (Box 4)
- Histories and Constitutions 1914-1999
  The Histories and Constitutions, 1914-1999 (0.25 linear ft.), series includes editions and revisions of the Galens' constitution and by-laws between 1914 and 1994. The Galens have also produced multiple histories and summaries about the society and its activities. In the 1950s, Galens reexamined old minutes and records, and compiled yearly histories between 1914 and 1948. These annual histories provide valuable information about years that are sparsely represented in other parts of this record group. The 1955 published history by Marvin J. Lubeck provides detailed information about the early years of the Galens, and the unpublished 1984 history by Donald M. Black contains photocopies of photographs and a few editions of the infamous Thymico-Lymphatic Constitutions.
  - Annual Histories
    - 1914-1930 (Box 4)
    - 1931-1948 (Box 4)
  - Articles of Incorporation 1959 (Box 4)
  - Constitutions and By-Laws
    - 1914, 1948 (Box 4)
    - 1959, 1960, 1962 (Box 4)
    - 1964, 1970, 1974, 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1977, 1982, 1983 (Box 4)
    - 1990, 1991, 1994 (Box 4)
  - "Galens Honorary Medical Society," by Donald M. Black 1984 (Box 4)
    (includes a photocopy of the 1948 Thymico-Lymphatic Constitution)
  - Historian-Constitution Committee 1957, 1964, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Historical Committee 1984-1989 (scattered) (Box 4)
  - "History of the Galens Honorary Medical Society," by Marvin J. Lubeck University of Michigan Medical Bulletin, vol. 21, February 1955 pp. 41-50. (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Histories 1989, 1993, 1999 undated (Box 4)
  - Summaries of Activities 1914-1958, 1928-1981 (Box 4)
- Membership 1914-1999
  The Membership, 1914-1999 (0.25 linear ft.), series includes scattered information about past Galens members. A large portion of the series consists of an Alumni Questionnaire conducted in 1961. The questionnaire collected information from past members about their professional status as of 1961. Other materials in this series include scattered member lists, alumni correspondence and alumni directories.
  - Alumni Advisory Board 1958, 1960 undated (Box 4)
  - Alumni Committees 1959-1980 (scattered) (Box 4)
  - Alumni Correspondence 1955-1999 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Directories 1961, 1964, 1969, 1975, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Questionnaire 1961
    - A-G (Box 4)
    - H-P (Box 4)
    - Q-Z (Box 4)
  - Honorary Members List 1927-1950, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Membership Committee 1972-1994 (scattered) (Box 4)
  - Members List 1914-1958, 1978-1988 (Box 4)
  - Prefects List 1914-1960 (Box 4)
  - Presidents List 1914-1971 (Box 4)
- Audio-Visual Material 1927-2005
  The Audio-Visual Material, 1927-2005 (1.0 linear ft.), series includes scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, and audio/video recordings. The scrapbooks in the collection have been disbound for improved storage and preservation. The Camp Champ scrapbook highlights the Galens involvement with that organization in 1986. There are three folders of pages from a scrapbook compiled between 1940 and 1949. This scrapbook documents, through photographs and captions, the Galens activities during that time, including tag days, initiation banquets, lectures, and picnics. The final scrapbook chronicles the history of Galens from its inception in 1914 through 1985 with the use of photographs, text, and clippings. While this scrapbook has been disbound in order to better preserve the materials, a photocopy of the original scrapbook and the contents of the scrapbook are contained in separate folders in the series. Loose photographs show the Galens' initiation banquet, lectureship, the silver shovel award, and various Tag Day poster children. The clippings folder focuses on Tag Days. There is also one reel-to-reel audio tape of the 1980 smoker and six VHS videotapes and two DVDs of Galens Smokers between 1989 and 2005.
  - Camp Champ Scrapbook 1986 (Box 5)
  - Clippings 1944-1995 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Folder 1
      - Lectureship 1965 (Box 5)
      - Shovel Award undated (Box 5)
      - Initiation Banquet 1950-1951, 2001 (Box 5)
      - Class of 1952, 1952 (Box 5)
      - Tag Day Children 1952, 1983, 1994 undated (Box 5)
    - Folder 2
      - Tag Days 1964-1965, undated (Box 5)
      - Smoker 1961 (Box 5)
      - Smoker 1965 (Box 5)
      - "My Fair Malady" 1977 (Box 5)
      - Group Photograph undated (Box 5)
      - Smoker undated (Box 5)
      - Galens Workshop undated (Box 5)
    - Alumni Reunion Banquet 1964 (Box 5)
    - Galens Shop (annotated pages) undated (Box 5)
    - Group Shots undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Galens (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook Pages (annotated) 1940-1948, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Scrapbook Chronicling Galens History 1927-1985
      - Photocopy of original scrapbook (Box 5)
      - Contents of original scrapbook (removed to a folder) (Box 5)
  - Smokers
    - Smoker, "The Sound of Mucus", 1980 April 23, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 3 3/4 ips
      [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
      - [Part 1], [9859-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (Sound recording of the 1980 Smoker. Comedic performance produced by Medical Students at the University of Michigan.)
      - [Part 2], [9859-SR-1-2]; mp3 file; (Sound recording of the 1980 Smoker. Comedic performance produced by Medical Students at the University of Michigan.)
    - "Meccalot," April 7, 1989 (Box 5)
      (videotaped event, VHS magnetic tape, 3/4 inch videocassette, duration unknown)
    - "Little Lab of Horrors," March 30-31, 1990 (Box 5)
      (videotaped event, VHS magnetic tape, 3/4 inch videocassette, duration 2:15:45)
    - "The Little Dermaid," April 3, 1993 (Box 5)
    - "Star Wards," April 2, 1994 (Box 5)
    - "Clue Cells," 2003 (videotaped event, 2 VHS magnetic tape, 3/4 inch videocassettes) (Box 5)
    - "Clue Cells," 2003, DVD (Box 5)
    - "Revenge of the GERD," 2005, DVD (Box 5)
- Funds 1952-1990
  The Funds, 1952-1990 (1.0 linear ft.), series includes statements and summaries of the major bank accounts maintained by Galens; namely the General, Children's, and University funds. Information in this series is contained in handwritten spreadsheets and ledgers kept by the treasurer and in printed statements received from Galens' primary banking institutions.
  - Balance Sheets (all funds) (Box 6)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 6)